Guide to the Paula L. Ettelbrick papers,1986-1993.
Ettelbrick, Paula L. papers,1986-1993.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Paula L. Ettelbrick papers, 1986-1993.
7644
Paula L. Ettelbrick
5.6 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, subject files.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Court orders and files relating to the Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund's pioneering work on second parent adoption. Included are files on: second parent adoption, other adoption cases, co-parenting cases, and domestic partners. Also, files on marital status discrimination, health, sodomy laws, violence, and a federal civil rights law.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ettelbrick served as staff attorney and then legal director of the Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund from 1986-1993. She went on to leadership positions at the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force, the International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Commission, and the Stonewall Community Foundation. She was born October 2, 1955 and died October 7, 2011.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Court orders and files relating to the Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund's pioneering work on second parent adoption, a legal principle that makes it possible for the same sex partner of a parent to become the legal second parent. Included are files on: second parent adoption, other adoption cases, co-parenting cases, and domestic partners. Also, files on other lesbian and gay rights issues that Ettelbrick focused on while working with Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, including marital status discrimination, health, sodomy laws, violence, and a federal civil rights law.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ettelbrick, Paula L.; Lambda Legal Defense & Education Fund.
Subjects:
Gay adoption--New York (State); Gay parents--New York (State); Gay rights--Law and legislation.; Lesbian mothers--New York (State); Gays--Legal status, laws, etc.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection.
CONTAINER LIST
- Adoption, Second Parent: "In matter of Michael David", California, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Second Parent Adoption: Illinois, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Second Parent Adoption: "In re: Katherine Mary" (Massachusetts), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Second Parent Adoption: "In matter of W.S.D.? District of Columbia", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Second Parent Adoption: New Mexico, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Second Parent Adoption: Minnesota, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Second Parent Adoption: "In re: R.C. ? Vermont", 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Second Parent Adoption: Wisconsin, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Second Parent Adoption: New York Attorney General Opinion, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Second Parent Adoption: New York Attorney General Opinion, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Second Parent Adoption: Full Faith and Credit (Georgia Context), 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Second Parent Adoption: Miscellaneous Adoptions, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Second Parent Adoption: "In re: Evan, New York", 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Second Parent Adoption: New York Miscellaneous, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Second Parent Adoption: Pennsylvania, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Multiple Parent Adoption: "In re: A.L. and E.L.", Oregon, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Second Parent Adoption: Hennepin County, Minnesota, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Second Parent Adoption: "Garry/ Opatut", New Jersey, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Second Parent Adoption: Vermont legislation [with computer diskettes], 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Second Parent Adoption: Vermont legislation, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Second Parent Adoption: "Matter of L.S. and V.L.", District of Columbia, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Second Parent Adoption: "In re: AA; In re: B.L.V.B.", Vermont, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Adoption: Miscellaneous articles, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Adoption: Parenting, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Adoption or Co-parenting: New Jersey, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Adoption: B. Gressin, Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Adoption: "Matter of adoption of Hope, New York", 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Adoption: Florida, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Adoption: New York, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Adoption: "Sabol v. Farie" (Florida), 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Co-parent adoption papers, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Parenting: Co-parents, 1989-190 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Co-parenting: Colorado, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Co-parenting cases: "Matter of Pearlman" (Florida), 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Co-parenting cases: "Michele G. v. Nancy S."(California), 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Co-Parenting: A.C. v. C.B. (New Mexico) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Co-Parenting: Carney v. Dianna (Maryland) (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Co-Parenting: Estate of Hamilton (Vermont) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Co-Parenting: Kulla v. McNulty (Minnesota) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Co-Parenting: Loftin v. Flournoy (California) (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Co-Parenting: Matter of Batey (California) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Co-Parenting: Matter of Hatzopoulos (Colorado) (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Co-Parenting: Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- Co-Parenting: New Hampshire Research (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Co-Parenting: Prescott v. Blume (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Co-Parenting: Sabol v. Bowling (California) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Co-Parenting: Sofia De Felice, - (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Co-Parenting: Sporleder v. Hermes (Wisconson) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Co-Parenting: Statutes (Oregon) (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Co-Parenting: Steven W. v. Martha N. (California) (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Domestic Partners: Insurance Issues (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Domestic Partners: Lotus Development Corporation (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Domestic Partners: Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
- Domestic Partners: Montefiore Hospital (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Domestic Partners: Private Employers, General (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
- Domestic Partners: Unions (Local 715 SEIU) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Age - Old Lesbians, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Alison D., 1990 (Box 4, Folder 2-7)
- Constitutional Law, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Employment: Miscellaneous, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Employment: Articles, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Employment: California Cases, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Employment: City/Local Laws, 1988-1991 (Box 4, Folder 12-15)
- Employment: Family Leave Act, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Employment: International, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Employment: National Employment Lawyers Association, 19904992 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Employment: Research - Title VII, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Employment: Research - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
- Employment: Sexual Harrassment - Federal Law, 1986-1992 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Employment: State Laws, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Experts: Couples, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Experts: Garnets (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Experts: General, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
- Experts: Herek, Gregory, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Experts: Herek, Gregory, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Experts: Parenting, 1989-1991 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Federal Civil Rights Bill: Congressional Hearing Material (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Federal Civil Rights Bill: Congressional Hearing Material (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Federal Civil Rights Bill: Religious Exemption (Box 5, Folder 3)
- General Reading Material, 1989-1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- GMHC (Gay Men's Health Crisis): Lesbian AIDS Project, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Health: ADAP, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Health: Health Care Campaign Coalition, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Health: H.M.O.'s/ Health Providers, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Marital Status Discrimination/Religious Freedom, 1992-1996 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Initiatives: [Colorado], 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Initiatives: NGLTF -Fight the Right Resource Packet, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Initiatives: [Miscellaneous], 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
- International: Civil Rights, 1990-1994 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- International: ILGA (International Gay and Lesbian Association), 1992 (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
- International: ILGA Women's Secretariat, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- International: Information, 1990-1994 (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
- International: International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Commission, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- International: Stonewall 25, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Lesbian and Gay Studies: Articles, 1966-1993 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Lesbian and Gay Studies: C.L.A.G.S., 1991 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Lesbian and Gay Studies: Homosexuality and Gender (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Lesbian and Gay Studies: Homosexuality and Biology, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Marital Status Discrimination/Religious Freedom, 1992-1996 (Box 5, Folder 27-29)
- Relationship Contract/Recognition Cases: Crooke v. Gilden (Georgia), 1992 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Relationship Contract/Recognition Cases: Matter of Kowalski, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Relationship Contract/Recognition Cases: Miscellaneous, 1991-1993 (Box 5, Folder 32-33)
- Relationship Contract/Recognition Cases: Shahar v. Bowers (Georgia), 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Sexual Harrassment: CWELF Report, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Sexual Harrassment: Dillon v. Frank (California), 1992 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Sexual Harrassment: Lesbian/Gay, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Sexual Harrassment: Robinson v. Jackson Shipyards, Inc., 1991 (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Sodomy Laws: [Kentucky v. Wasson et. al.l, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Sodomy Laws: [Michigan Organization for Human Rights v. Kelley], 1990 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Sodomy Laws: Nicaragua, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Sodomy Laws: Texas Law and Mica England Complaint, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Sodomy Laws: Texas v. Morales et al., 1992 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Universities: Law Students: Organizations, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Universities: University of Michigan Law School, 1991-1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Violence: Violence Against Women Act, 1986-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Violence: Anti-Gay, 1989-1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Violence: Anti-Gay Studies, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Violence: AJC Publications [American Jewish Committee], 1992 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Violence: Bias Bill, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Violence: Christian Coalition Agenda, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Violence: Domestic Violence, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Violence: Domestic Violence Act (NJ), 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Violence: Hate Crimes: Hate Speech/Hate Crimes, 1989-1992 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Violence: Hate Crimes: [Representing Victims of Bias Crimes], 1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Violence: Hate Crimes: Skinheads, 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Violence: Hate Crimes: [Striking Back At Bigotry], 1986 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Women's Studies: General Information, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 15)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
The following periodicals have been removed from the collection and catalogued individually:
Agenda. New York: 1998: Spring, Summer, Fall/Winter (2).
Anti-Sexism Newsletter. 1989:v.4no.l. 1990:v.4,no.4.
Center Voice. 1988: v.4,no. 1-2, 4.
Christopher Street. 1988:v.10 no. 12.
Edge Newsletter: Education in a Disabled Gay Environmen t. 1988:v.2no. 1.
Empire State Pride Agenda Quarterly Update. 1990: December. 1991: Winter.
EqualTimes. 1988:v.lno.4-5. 1989:v.l no.6, 11.
FAIRPAC Quarterly Update. 1988: Winter. 1989: Spring. 1990: Fall-Spring; special election issue: Oct. 1990.
GFN (Gay Friends and Neighbors). 1988:v.6 no.2-5.
GLIDNews. 1990: February.
ILGA Bulletin. 1991: no. 1-2,4-5. 1992:no.4.
Lesbian Her story Archives Newsletter 10. 1988: February.
Lovetann. 1993: January.
Momentum. 1988: Winter. 1990: Winter.
Newsweek. 1990: v. 115 no. 11.
NWSActuib, 1989:v.2,no.4.
Outweek. 1989:no. 19, 20, 22, 27. 1990:no. 28, 37, 58-9, 68, 71-3, 76.
ParleePlus. 1990:v.15 no.8, 10.
Pride Agenda Members Update. 1993: Spring. 1995: Summer.
Pride Guide New York, 1983, 1988-90.
Research Report. 1990: v.9no.2.
Sappho's Isle. 1990:v.3no.2.
Stop the Violence. 1992:no.8
Visibilities. 1989:v.l no.2
Women 's Research Network News. 1989: v.2no. 1.
Working It Ou t. 1992: v. 1 ,no.2.